International Union of Immunological Societies records
International Union of Immunological Societies records
1966-2011
bulk 1971-1997
1966 2011
Coll009
International Union of Immunological Societies
39 boxes (18.5 linear feet)
39 boxes
18.5 linear feet
Records document the history and development of the International Union of Immunological Societies (IUIS). The correspondence, council and general-assembly meeting minutes, agendas, reports, accounting, and membership files provide a clear view of the early growth of the Union. Extensive Committee files such as those for the Standardization Committee, the Nomenclature Committee, the Clinical Immunology Committee, the Veterinary Immunology Committee and others illustrate the interests and activities of the IUIS. In addition, there is significant documentation for the meetings of International Congress of Immunology, considered one of the most important functions of the organization.
University of Maryland, Baltimore County Albin O. Kuhn Library and Gallery UMBC 1000 Hilltop Circle Baltimore, MD 21250 410-455-2353 speccoll@umbc.edu
This collection of records of the International Union of Immunological Societies 1966 – 2011 documents the origins of the Union, its growth in membership and committees and the developments in the International Congress of Immunology. These records have been organized into five series: Officers and Council, Membership, Meetings, Committees, and Affiliated Organizations.
The first series, Officers and Council, contains the correspondence and reports of the president, vice-president, secretary-general and treasurer, the minutes, agendas, reports, and correspondence of the meetings of council, the organization’s financial records and some miscellaneous administrative files and photos. There is a complete run of correspondence for the President from 1971, the date of the beginning of the Union through 2001 and a nearly complete run of Treasurer’s correspondence. The correspondence files for the Vice-President and Secretary-General are considerably more sporadic. Of particular interest are some of the early correspondences dating as early as 1966 detailing the discussions leading up to the founding of IUIS, decisions pertaining to the choice of name, issues relating to the proposed constitution and the organization of the first IUIS Committees, Standardization and Nomenclature. Also of note is a compact disc from 2004 containing the electronic files of the Secretary General Anne Kelso, which includes files regarding archives, the assembly, committees, 2007 International Congress planning, the IUIS council, database, email correspondence, federations, finances, ICSU, IUIS central office, IUIS handbook, letters, materials for the website, membership applications, and WHO documents ranging in dates from 1999 to 2004.
This series also contains the minutes of all the council meetings beginning with the 1970 meeting and continuing up to 2011. Agendas, reports, correspondence and other materials connected with these meetings are, however, only available from 1979 - 1997. A large selection of the meeting minutes are available through UMBC's Digital Collections.
There are a small number of President’s reports and very few reports of the Secretary-General but there is a reasonably good run of Treasurer’s reports. There is one copy of the 1st International Congress budget for 1971 and another financial report for 1973 after which there is a fairly good run of treasurer’s reports for the years 1980 – 1995.
The accounting records available in this collection are practically non-existent for the first ten years of the organization. There is a pair of handwritten ledgers for the year 1972 and then nothing until 1982. Records from 1982 forward include banking and investment information, files pertaining to income and expenditures including invoices, receipts, budgets, and audits, and files concerning the expenses of specific committees.
The second series, Membership, comprises the bulk of the records that relate to dues, subscription, member societies and regional federations. There are an extensive number of invoices, receipts, and correspondences pertaining to member payments, as well as correspondence files that provide information about the relationship of IUIS with immunological societies and regional federations throughout the world. These together with printed membership directories show the growth of the Union over time.
Series three, Meetings, primarily holds documents relating to the International Congresses on Immunology but also include some records for the IUIS Conference on Clinical Immunology, and the International Immunopathological Symposium. The files include the minutes of the General Assembly, as well as agendas, reports and budgets, programs and correspondence. There are also a significant number of files relating to the planning and arrangements for the congresses. These include schedules, contracts, proposals, brochures, budgets, ephemera correspondence, memos, and management agreements.
The files in the fourth series, Committees, are the records of the actions of eight IUIS committees. Some of the committees have retained very few documents while others such as the Clinical Immunology Committee, the Nomenclature Committee, the Standardization Committee and the Symposia Committee have records spanning most of the time they have been functioning. Of the IUIS committees the Veterinary Immunology Committee has maintained most extensive record of their work. Committee files include some or all of the following: correspondence, memos, minutes, agendas, proposals, budgets, reports, articles, programs, and a questionnaire. Of some interest are the correspondences and reports of the Clinical Immunology Committee that predate its organization. They provide a view into the concerns that lead up to its formation.
The last series is Affiliate Organizations. These records pertain to organizations that have some type of formal working relationship with IUIS. For most of the represented organizations there is very little material present but the records do include some correspondence, memos, reports, and a charter. On the other hand, there is quite a substantial amount of documents for the International Council of Scientific Union (ICSU). These files contain correspondence, audited accounts, dues and exchange rate information, grants, reports, and newsletters.
In the early 1960’s it became clear to many investigators, who thought of themselves as immunologists, that they needed an international network that would both promote interaction between immunologists and present their aspirations and needs to international and national institutions. At the time national societies had long existed in the United States and Great Britain, but such societies had just recently been founded in Canada, Israel, Switzerland, France, and Australia and others were on the point of formation. As the result of informal consultation among immunologists, the International Union of Immunological Societies (IUIS), an umbrella organization for regional and national societies of immunology throughout the world, was officially founded in Brugge (Belgium) on May 5, 1969 by the representatives of ten Societies (American Association of Immunologists, British Society for Immunology, Canadian Society for Immunology, Dutch Society for Immunology, Gesellschaft fur Immunologie, Israel Immunological Society, Polish Society of Immunology, Scandinavian Society for Immunology, Societe Francaise d’immunologie, Yugoslav Immunological Society). The representatives of the Australian Society for Immunology and the Swiss Society of Allergy and Immunology were unable to attend but the societies expressed their support and were later accepted as founding members.
At this first meeting of the Council, officers were elected, a committee structure was established, and steps were taken to write a constitution. Additional Council meetings were held on September 2, 1970 in Merlingen, Switzerland, on February 23, 1971 in London, England, and on July 30, 1971 in Washington D.C. The IUIS Constitution prepared by the Council was formally approved by the 1st General Assembly of IUIS. (The Constitution was revised and adopted by the General Assembly in 1995.) The objectives articulated in the Constitution were: to organize international cooperation in immunology and to promote communication between the various branches of immunology and allied subjects; to encourage co-operation between independent Societies that represent the interests of immunology; and to contribute to the advancement of immunology in all its aspects.
The General Assembly also elected the first official slate of IUIS officers and a new Council who would serve for the period 1971 – 1974, in accordance with the rules of the IUIS Constitution. These rules stated that new officers and members were to be elected at the triennial General Assembly. As a result of this election Bernard Cinader became the first President, John Humphrey Vice – President, Alain de Weck Secretary – General, and Peter Miescher Treasurer.
The first and most important decision of the new IUIS involved the creation of the International Congress of Immunology. The need to create international congresses that would allow immunologists of many different sub disciplines to present their particular point of view to colleagues in other sub-disciplines had long been apparent and it was unanimously decided that an International meeting, covering the many different areas of contemporary immunology should be organized. The organizationof the first International Congress of Immunology was entrusted to the American Association of Immunologists, founded in 1913, the oldest national immunological society, and was held on August 1-6,1971 in Washington DC. More than 3400 scientists representing 45 countries came to participate in fifteen symposia and eighty-four workshops encompassing most aspects of modern immunology. The second International Congress was held in Brighton, England on July 21 – 26, 1974 and was attended by approximately 4500 scientists who participated in twenty-five Symposia and one hundred sixty-three Workshops. Subsequent congresses have been held every three years under the auspices of IUIS.
The establishment of committees was a key factor in the initial development of IUIS. In the first year Committees on Standardization, Nomenclature, Education and Symposia were organized. Two of these, Standardization and Nomenclature were already operating by the time of the First International Congress. Shortly thereafter, in 1973, the Clinical Immunology Committee was formed. These five committees remained as the major focus of IUIS activities until the early 1980’s. In 1980, the Veterinary Immunology Committee was added, followed quickly by the establishment of the Publications Committee in 1981.
An important objective for IUIS was to interact with international scientific organizations such as the World Health Organization (WHO) and the International Council of Scientific Unions (ICSU). Immunology had become a separate section of WHO in 1963 and from its beginnings IUIS maintained an intimate, cooperative relationship with all aspects of WHO immunological activities. From the outset they participated in joint committees in the areas of nomenclature and standardization. Then, in 1976, the IUIS was accepted as a member of the International Council of Scientific Unions.
The Immunologist, the official journal of IUIS, published it’s first issue in 1993. The journal publishes articles and reviews in basic and clinical immunology and provides a forum for discussing issues of importance for the discipline of immunology.
In the year 2012 there were 65 member societies of IUIS, many of which belong to one of four Regional Federations.
Organized into five series: Series I. Officers and Council, 1966-2011. Series II. Membership, 1971-2001. Series III. Meetings, 1970-2010. Series IV. Committees, 1967-2000. Series V. Affiliated Societies, 1972-2000.
Series I. Officers and Council
Correspondence
Council Meetings
Reports
Miscellany
Accounting
Series II. Membership
Member Payments
Member Societies and Regional Federations
Directories
Series III. Meetings
Series IV. Committees
Organization
Clinical Immunology
Commission for Europe
Education
Nomenclature
Publication
Standardization
Symposia
Veterinary Immunology
Series V. Affiliated Organizations
European Federation of Immunological Societies (EFIS)
International Training & Research Center (ITR)
World Health Organization (WHO)
International Council of Scientific Unions (ICSU)
Miscellaneous Organizations
No restrictions.
Finding aid available.
This collection came to the archives in fourteen different accessions: MSS 95-02 donated by Alain De Weck of the Inselspital Institut fur Immunlolgie umd Allergologie. Bern, Switzerland on April 19, 1995. MSS 95-10 donated by Gustof Nossal of the Walter and Eliza Hall Institute of Medical Research, The Royal Melbourne Hospital. Victoria, Australia on July 17, 1995. MSS 95-14 donated by Richard G. Miller of University of Toronto department of Medical Biophysics. Toronto, Ontario, Canada on September 18, 1995. MSS 96-09 donated by Bernard Charley of the Virologie et Immunologie Moleculaires, INRA. Jouy en Josas, France on April 2, 1996. MSS 96-10 donated by Michael Sela of the Department of Immunology, Weizman Institute of Science, Israel on April 25, 1996. MSS 99-01 donated by Bernard Charley of the Virologie et Immunologie Moleculaires, INRA. Jouy en Josas, France on January 11, 1999 SARCV 99-05 donated by Keith James of the Lester Research Labs., University Department of Surgery, Royal Infirmary. Edinburgh, Scotland on May 20, 1999. SARCV 99-07 donated by Henry Metzger of NIAMS, NIH. Bethesda, Maryland on August 20, 1999. SARCV 2000-06 donated by P. Nieuwenhuis of the Histology dept. University of Groningen. Gironingen, Netherlands on May 30, 2000. SARCV 2004-06 donated by the International Union of Immunological Societies on September 28, 2004. SARCV 2005-02 donated by the International Union of Immunological Societies on April 11, 2004. SARCV 2005-04 donated by the International Union of Immunological Societies on June 1, 2005. SARCV 2011-02 donated by Gerlinde Jahn of the Vienna Medical Academy. SARCV 2011-03 donated by Masayuki Miyasaka of Osaka University Graduate School of Medicine.
Immunology Societies, etc.; IUIS Archives; Yugoslav Immunological Society Archives; Yugoslav War, 1991-1995 Social aspects; Yugoslav Immunological Society
- Series I. Officers & Council, 1966-2011; 1971-1997 bulk; 23 boxes (9.5 linear feet)
  The correspondence, minutes, agendas, reports, and financial records of the society officers and council meetings are arranged into five subseries by activity.
  - Subseries I.A. Correspondence, 1966-2001; 10 boxes (4 linear feet)
    Correspondence files are arranged in date order and then subsequently in alphabetical order by office.
    - 1966 – 1969 (Jan - July) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 1969 (Aug – Dec) (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 1970 (Jan – March) (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 1970 (April – May) (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 1970 (June – Aug) (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 1970 (Sept – Dec) (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 1971 Council (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 1971 President (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - 1971 Secretary – General (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - 1971 Secretary – General (2nd International Congress – Planning) (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - 1972 Council (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - 1972 President (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - 1972 Secretary – General (2nd International Congress – Planning) (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - 1973 President (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - 1973 Secretary – General (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - 1974 President (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - 1974 Secretary – General (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - 1977 President (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - 1977 Secretary – General (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - 1977 Treasurer (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - 1978 Council (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - 1978 President (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - 1978 President (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - 1979 President (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - 1979 Treasurer (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - 1980 President (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - 1980 Secretary – General (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - 1980 Treasurer (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - 1981 President (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - 1981 Secretary – General (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - 1981 Treasurer (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - 1982 President (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - 1982 Secretary – General (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - 1982 Treasurer (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - 1983 President (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - 1983 Secretary – General (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - 1983 Treasurer (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - 1983 Vice - President (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - 1984 Treasurer (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - 1984 Vice - President (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - 1985 Treasurer (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - 1985 (Jan – June) Vice – President (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - 1985 (July – Sept) Vice – President (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - 1985 (Sept – Dec) Vice – President (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - 1986 (Jan – June) President (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - 1986 (July – Aug) President (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - 1986 (Aug – Dec) President (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - 1986 Treasurer (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - 1987 (Jan – April) President (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - 1987 (May – June) President (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - 1987 (July – Dec) President (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - 1987 Treasurer (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - 1988 (Jan – June) President (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - 1988 (July – Sept) President (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - 1988 (Oct – Dec) President (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - 1988 Treasurer (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - 1989 (Jan – May) President (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - 1989 (June – Oct) President (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - 1989 Secretary – General (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - 1989 Treasurer (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - 1990 President (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - 1990 Past - President (Nossal) (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - 1990 Secretary-General (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - 1990 Treasurer (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - 1990 Vice – President (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - 1991 Past – President (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - 1991 President (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - 1991 Treasurer (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - 1991 Vice - President (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - 1992 Council (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - 1992 Past - President (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - 1992 President (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - 1992 Secretary-General (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - 1992 (Jan – June) Treasurer (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - 1992 (July – Dec) Treasurer (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - 1993 Council (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - 1993 Past – President & Editor in Chief of “The Immunologist” (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - 1993 President (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - 1993 Secretary-General (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - 1993 Treasurer (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - 1994 Past – President & Editor in Chief of “The Immunologist” (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - 1994 President (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - 1994 Secretary-General (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - 1994 Treasurer (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - 1994 Vice - President (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - 1995 Council (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - 1995 Past - President & Editor in Chief of "The Immunologist" (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - 1995 President (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - 1995 Secretary-General (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - 1995 Treasurer (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - 1995 Vice - President (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - 1996 Past - President (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - 1996 President (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - 1996 Secretary-General (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - 1996 Treasurer (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - 1996 Vice - President (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - 1997 Past - President (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - 1997 Past - President & Editor in Chief of "The Immunologist" (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - 1997 President (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - 1997 Secretary-General (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - 1997 Treasurer (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - 1998 Past - President (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - 1998 Past - President & Editor in Chief of "The Immunologist" (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - 1998 President (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - 1998 Secretary-General (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - 1998 Treasurer (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - 1999 President (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - 1999 Secretary-General (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - 2000 President (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - 2000 Secretary-General (Box 10, Folder 13)
    - 2001 Past - President (Box 10, Folder 14)
    - 2001 Past - Secretary-General (Box 10, Folder 15)
    - 2001 President (Box 10, Folder 16)
    - 2001 Secretary-General (Box 10, Folder 17)
    - 2004 Secretary-General Electronic Files (Box 10, Folder 18)
  - Subseries I.B. Countil Meetings, 1970-2010; 4.5 boxes (2 linear feet)
    Meeting minutes, agendas, reports and correspondence arranged by meeting date and then by document type.
    - 1970 Minutes (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - 1971 Minutes (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - 1972 Minutes (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - 1973 Minutes (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - 1974 Minutes (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - 1974 Minutes (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - 1975 Minutes (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - 1976 Minutes (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - 1977 Minutes (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - 1977 Minutes (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - 1978 Minutes (Digital file available) (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - 1979 Correspondence (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - 1979 Minutes (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - 1979 Reports, Agendas, & Misc (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - 1980 Minutes (Box 11, Folder 13)
    - 1981 Correspondence (Box 11, Folder 14)
    - 1981 Minutes (Box 11, Folder 15)
    - 1981 Reports, Agendas, & Misc (Box 11, Folder 16)
    - 1982 Correspondence (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - 1982 Minutes (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - 1982 Reports, Agendas, & Misc (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - 1983 Minutes (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - 1984 Minutes (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - 1984 Reports, Agendas, & Misc (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - 1985 Correspondence (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - 1985 Minutes (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - 1985 Reports, Agendas, & Misc. (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - 1986 Correspondence (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - 1986 Minutes (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - 1986 Reports, Agendas, & Misc. (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - 1987 Minutes (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - 1987 Reports, Agendas, & Misc (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - 1988 Minutes (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - 1988 Reports, Agendas, & Misc (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - 1989 Minutes (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - 1989 Reports, Agendas, & Misc (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - 1990 Minutes (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - 1990 Reports, Agendas, & Misc (Box 13, Folder 10)
    - 1991 Minutes (Box 13, Folder 11)
    - 1991 Reports, Agendas, & Misc (Box 13, Folder 12)
    - 1992 Correspondence (Box 13, Folder 13)
    - 1992 Minutes (Box 13, Folder 14)
    - 1992 Minutes (Box 13, Folder 14)
    - 1992 Reports, Agendas, & Misc (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - 1993 Minutes (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - 1994 Minutes (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - 1995 Agendas, Correspondence, & Notes (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - 1995 Minutes (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - 1995 Minutes (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - 1996 Agenda (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - 1996 Minutes (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - 1996 Notebook (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - 1997 Minutes (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - 1997 Reports & Agendas (Box 14, Folder 10)
    - 1998 Minutes (1 of 3) (Box 14, Folder 11)
    - 1998 Minutes (1 of 3) (Box 14, Folder 11)
    - 1998 Minutes (2 of 3) (Box 14, Folder 12)
    - 1998 Minutes (3 of 3) (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - 2000 Minutes (1 of 3) (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - 2000 Minutes (1 of 3) (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - 2000 Minutes (2 of 3) (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - 2000 Minutes (3 of 3) (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - 2001 Minutes (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - 2001 Minutes (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - 2001 Minutes (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - 2001 Minutes (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - 2002 Minutes (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - 2003 Minutes (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - 2004 Minutes (Box 15, Folder 8)
    - 2004 Minutes (Box 15, Folder 8)
    - 2004 Minutes (Box 15, Folder 8)
    - 2005 Minutes (Box 15, Folder 9)
    - 2006 Minutes (Box 15, Folder 10)
    - 2007 Minutes (Box 15, Folder 11)
    - 2007 Minutes (Box 15, Folder 11)
    - 2008 Minutes (Box 15, Folder 12)